<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Howto | Om Prakash Singh]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.omps.in/blog/categories/howto/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.omps.in/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-29T14:17:48+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://www.omps.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Om Prakash Singh]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[omps@omps.in]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tweet Posts With Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.omps.in/blog/2016/04/24/howto-tweet-new-posts-in-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-24T08:19:20+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://www.omps.in/blog/2016/04/24/howto-tweet-new-posts-in-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to the <a href="http://fusion94.org/blog/2013/01/13/howto-tweet-new-posts-in-octopress/">blog post</a> by <a href="http://fusion94.org">Tony Guntharp</a> who got inspired from another blog post by <a href="http://blog.prydoni.us">Adnan Abdulhussein</a> on how to integrate twitter posting with <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>. His post was some 3 Years old and the <a href="https://github.com/sferik/twitter">twitter gem</a> for <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> version <code>5.16.0</code> has gone through a lot of changes, So technically I did some rewrite into the ruby configuration code and fixed it so I can post the tweets with the latest twitter gem.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The basic idea remains the same taken from the predecessors blogs, you create a post and print the tweet message you want to give and it create a link to the post in the tweet_queue file. When the <code>rake deploy</code> task is called, it reads from the <strong>tweet_queue</strong> file and tweets what&rsquo;s in their line by line. This way you can create multiple posts at a time, and they all will be tweeted when you run your <code>rake deploy</code> task for your blog.</p>

<h3>Create a twitter application.</h3>

<p>A twitter application is must to post to <a href="http://www.twitter.com">twitter</a>. Head over to <a href="https://apps.twitter.com/app/new,">https://apps.twitter.com/app/new,</a> sign in and create a new application for your blog.</p>

<p>In <em>settings</em>: ensure <em>read</em> and <em>write</em> is <strong>enabled</strong>.</p>

<p>In <em>Keys and access tokens</em>: take note of the following details.</p>

<ul>
<li>Consumer Keys</li>
<li>Consumer Secret</li>
<li>Access Token</li>
<li>Access Token Secret</li>
</ul>


<h3>Install the gem</h3>

<p>We&rsquo;ll be using the <a href="https://github.com/sferik/twitter">twitter gem</a> to update the status. Put the below line in your development <code>Gemfile</code></p>

<pre><code>gem twitter
</code></pre>

<p>from the terminal run <code>bundle install</code></p>

<h3>Configure Octopress to use twitter gem</h3>

<p>Open the <code>Rakefile</code> in your favorite editor and add the below near the top with other required in the <code>Rakefile</code>.</p>

<pre><code>require twitter
</code></pre>

<p>Add the following lines after the <code>server_port</code> line</p>

<pre><code class="ruby Twitter Configuration">    # Twitter config (for tweeting posts)
    client = Twitter::REST::Client.new do |config|
      config.consumer_key = "YOUR_CONSUMER_KEY"
      config.consumer_secret = "YOUR_CONSUMER_SECRET"
      config.access_token = "YOUR_ACCESS_TOKEN""
      config.access_token_secret = "YOUR_ACCESS_TOKEN_SECRET
    end

    # MAKE SURE THERE IS A TRAILING SLASH, otherwise the linking won't work
    blog_url = "YOUR_BLOG_URL/"
</code></pre>

<p>ensure the trailing slash(/), It is required to append the date-name combination of the posts to form the url of the post.</p>

<h3>Modify the new_post rake task</h3>

<p>Search for <code>:new_post</code> rake task in the <code>Rakefile</code> and replace the task with the following.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby Modifying new_post task"># usage rake new_post[my-new-post] or rake new_post['my new post'] or rake new_post (defaults to "new-post")
desc "Begin a new post in #{source_dir}/#{posts_dir}"
task :new_post, :title, :tweet do |t, args|
  raise "### You haven't set anything up yet. First run `rake install` to set up an Octopress theme." unless File.directory?(source_dir)
  mkdir_p "#{source_dir}/#{posts_dir}"
  args.with_defaults(:title =&gt; 'new-post', :tweet =&gt; '')
  title = args.title
  filename = "#{source_dir}/#{posts_dir}/#{Time.now.strftime('%Y-%m-%d')}-#{title.to_url}.#{new_post_ext}"
  if File.exist?(filename)
    abort("rake aborted!") if ask("#{filename} already exists. Do you want to overwrite?", ['y', 'n']) == 'n'
  end
  puts "Creating new post: #{filename}"
  open(filename, 'w') do |post|
    post.puts "---"
    post.puts "layout: post"
    post.puts "title: \"#{title.gsub(/&amp;/,'&amp;amp;')}\""
    post.puts "date: #{Time.now.strftime('%Y-%m-%d %H:%M')}"
    post.puts "comments: true"
    post.puts "categories: "
    post.puts "---"
  end
  tweet = args.tweet
  if not tweet == ''
    # add to twitter status queue
    puts 'Adding post to tweet queue, it will be tweeted after deploying.'
    open('tweet_queue', 'a') do |file|
      file.puts "#{tweet} - #{blog_url}#{Time.now.strftime('%Y/%m/%d')}/#{title.to_url}/"
    end
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>If you already have a modified task, the only changes are the task declaration <code>(task :new_post, :title, :tweet do |t, args|)</code> and the last few lines starting with <code>tweet = args.tweet</code>.</p>

<h3>Setup to post tweets on deploy</h3>

<p>Look for the <code>deplpoy_task</code> in the <code>Rakefile</code> and change or replace the files accordingly.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby Deploy task">desc "Default deploy task"
task :deploy do
  # Check if preview posts exist, which should not be published
  if File.exists?(".preview-mode")
    puts "## Found posts in preview mode, regenerating files ..."
    File.delete(".preview-mode")
    Rake::Task[:generate].execute
  end

  Rake::Task[:copydot].invoke(source_dir, public_dir)
  Rake::Task["#{deploy_default}"].execute

  # Tweet
  next if not File.exists? 'tweet_queue'
  puts "Tweeting..."
  open('tweet_queue', 'r') do |file|
    while (line = file.gets)
      puts "Tweeting '#{line.gsub("\n", "")}' for @#{client.current_user.screen_name}..."
      client.update(line)
    end
  end
  puts "Deleting queue..."
  rm 'tweet_queue'
end
</code></pre>

<p>or just add the <code>#Tweet</code> task in deploy task.</p>

<h3>Usage</h3>

<p>Now while creating your <code>new_post</code> you need to specify a separate message for the tweet when you create a post. This is the best way to give you the option of choosing whether you want to tweet the post or not. It also allows you to add @’s and #’s to the tweet message separately from the post title.</p>

<p>For Example:</p>

<p>The first part is the URL, and the second part is your tweet message.</p>

<pre><code>rake new_post["HowTo Tweet New Posts in Octopress","HowTo Tweet New Posts in Octopress @twitter"]
</code></pre>

<p>You should be able to see your new post generated by the rake task.</p>

<p>Once, this is done. Go Ahead and write into your post and <code>rake gen_deploy</code> should do the rest of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working With Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.omps.in/blog/2016/04/23/working-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-23T11:58:21+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://www.omps.in/blog/2016/04/23/working-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Good old saturday.</h3>

<p>Well it is the good old saturday, when I planned to blog about something after around 2 weeks.</p>

<!--more-->


<h4>2 Weeks earlier</h4>

<p>Two weeks earlier I sat up, migrated my blog from pelican to octopress keeping the underlying githubpages intact, hardly did I know after two weeks, I will again face the similar problem like with pelican, In anycase this time I was determined not to rework again on migration to a new platform, and Instead I will fix what was missing and will try to resolve the issue with octopress only.</p>

<h4>Today</h4>

<p>My octopress did worked fine without any error, I made some cosmetic changes to the blog and published some post. The problem happened as the blog and the changes did not published, while I am making changes, the <code>rake deploy</code> did worked but I was not able to see anychanges happening to my blog page. But yes, the <code>rake preview</code> did worked fine and I was able to see my changes to localhost. Tried fixing it hard for sometimes but I didn&rsquo;t work.</p>

<p>To make it work, I deleted my github.io repository from github, ran the command <code>rake github_setup_pages</code> pushed the content from my local repository back to github again, and well, after this I was able to see the changes on the web. That&rsquo;s a releif.</p>

<p>Finally, I made some cosmetic changes, write this as my notes on to what happened and how I fixed it. I also need to find out why it failed in the first place, I am assuming I changed my Laptop, that could be a reason, but this I am not convinced by this.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
